<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<monster>
	      
	<name>Adult White Dragon</name>
	    
	<size>H</size>
	    
	<type>dragon</type>
	    
	<alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
	    
	<ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
	    
	<hp>200 (16d12+96)</hp>
	    
	<speed>walk 40 ft., burrow 30 ft., fly 80 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
	    
	<str>22</str>
	    
	<dex>10</dex>
	    
	<con>22</con>
	    
	<int>8</int>
	    
	<wis>12</wis>
	    
	<cha>12</cha>
	    
	<save>Dex +5, Con +11, Wis +6, Cha +6</save>
	    
	<skill>Perception +11, Stealth +5</skill>
	    
	<passive>21</passive>
	    
	<languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
	    
	<cr>13</cr>
	    
	<resist/>
	    
	<immune>cold</immune>
	    
	<vulnerable/>
	    
	<conditionImmune/>
	    
	<senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
	    
	<trait>
		        
		<name>Ice Walk</name>
		      
		<text>The dragon can move across and climb icy surfaces without needing to make an ability check. Additionally, difficult terrain composed of ice or snow doesn't cost it extra movement.</text>
		      
	</trait>
	    
	<trait>
		        
		<name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
		      
		<text>If the dragon fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
		      
	</trait>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Multiattack</name>
		      
		<text>The dragon can use its Frightful Presence. It then makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Bite</name>
		      
		<text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 17 (2d10 + 6) piercing damage plus 4 (1d8) cold damage.</text>
		      
		<attack>Bite|+11|2d10+6</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Claw</name>
		      
		<text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d6 + 6) slashing damage.</text>
		      
		<attack>Claw|+11|2d6+6</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Tail</name>
		      
		<text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 15 (2d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
		      
		<attack>Tail|+11|2d8+6</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Frightful Presence</name>
		      
		<text>Each creature of the dragon's choice that is within 120 feet of the dragon and aware of it must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to the dragon's Frightful Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Cold Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
		      
		<text>The dragon exhales an icy blast in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 19 Constitution saving throw, taking 54 (12d8) cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
		      
		<attack>Cold Breath (Recharge 5-6)||12d8</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<legendary>
		        
		<text>The dragon can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The dragon regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
		      
	</legendary>
	    
	<legendary>
		        
		<name>Detect</name>
		      
		<text>The dragon makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
		      
	</legendary>
	    
	<legendary>
		        
		<name>Tail Attack</name>
		      
		<text>The dragon makes a tail attack.</text>
		      
	</legendary>
	    
	<legendary>
		        
		<name>Wing Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
		      
		<text>The dragon beats its wings. Each creature within 10 feet of the dragon must succeed on a DC 19 Dexterity saving throw or take 13 (2d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. The dragon can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
		      
	</legendary>
	    
	<lair>
		        
		<name>Lair Actions</name>
		      
	</lair>
	    
	<lair>
		        
		<text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the dragon takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects; the dragon can't use the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
		      
		<text>• Freezing fog fills a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on a point the dragon can see within 120 feet of it. The fog spreads around corners, and its area is heavily obscured. Each creature in the fog when it appears must make a DC 10 Constitution saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature that ends its turn in the fog takes 10 (3d6) cold damage. A wind of at least 20 miles per hour disperses the fog. The fog otherwise lasts until the dragon uses this lair action again or until the dragon dies.</text>
		      
		<text>• Jagged ice shards fall from the ceiling, striking up to three creatures underneath that the dragon can see within 120 feet of it. The dragon makes one ranged attack roll (+7 to hit) against each target. On a hit, the target takes 10 (3d6) piercing damage.</text>
		      
		<text>• The dragon creates an opaque wall of ice on a solid surface it can see within 120 feet of it. The wall can be up to 30 feet long, 30 feet high, and 1 foot thick. When the wall appears, each creature within its area is pushed 5 feet out of the wall's space; appearing on whichever side of the wall it wants. Each 10-foot section of the wall has AC 5, 30 hit points, vulnerability to fire damage, and immunity to acid, cold, necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The wall disappears when the dragon uses this lair action again or when the dragon dies.</text>
		      
	</lair>
	    
	<lair>
		        
		<name>Regional Effects</name>
		      
	</lair>
	    
	<lair>
		        
		<text>The region containing a legendary white dragon's lair is warped by the dragon's magic, which creates one or more of the following effects:</text>
		      
		<text>• Chilly fog lightly obscures the land within 6 miles of the dragon's lair.</text>
		      
		<text>• Freezing precipitation falls within 6 miles of the dragon's lair, sometimes forming blizzard conditions when the dragon is at rest.</text>
		      
		<text>• Icy walls block off areas in the dragon's lair. Each wall is 6 inches thick, and a 10-foot section has AC 5, 15 hit points, vulnerability to fire damage, and immunity to acid, cold, necrotic, poison, and psychic damage.</text>
		      
		<text>• If the dragon wishes to move through a wall, it can do so without slowing down. The portion of the wall the dragon moves through is destroyed, however.</text>
		      
		<text>If the dragon dies, the fog and precipitation fade within 1 day. The ice walls melt over the course of 1d10 days.</text>
		      
	</lair>
	    
	<description>True dragons are winged reptiles of ancient lineage and fearsome power. They are known and feared for their predatory cunning and greed, with the oldest dragons accounted as some of the most powerful creatures in the world. Dragons are also magical creatures whose innate power fuels their dreaded breath weapons and other preternatural abilities.Many creatures, including wyverns and dragon turtles, have draconic blood. However, true dragons fall into the two broad categories of chromatic and metallic dragons. The black, blue, green, red, and white dragons are selfish, evil, and feared by all. The brass, bronze, copper, gold, and silver dragons are noble, good, and highly respected by the wise.Though their goals and ideals vary tremendously, all true dragons covet wealth, hoarding mounds of coins and gathering gems, jewels, and magic items. Dragons with large hoards are loath to leave them for long, venturing out of their lairs only to patrol or feed.True dragons pass through four distinct stages of life, from lowly wyrmlings to ancient dragons, which can live for over a thousand years. In that time, their might can become unrivaled and their hoards can grow beyond price.Dragon Age CategoriesCategory | Size | Age RangeWyrmling | Medium | 5 years or lessYoung | Large | 6–100 yearsAdult | Huge | 101–800 yearsAncient | Gargantuan | 801 years or moreSource: Monster Manual p. 101, Hoard of the Dragon Queen, Rise of Tiamat, Storm King's Thunder, Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage, Ghosts of Saltmarsh, Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus, Explorer's Guide to Wildemount</description>
	    
	<environment>arctic</environment>
	    
</monster>
