<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<monster>
	      
	<name>Cockatrice</name>
	    
	<size>S</size>
	    
	<type>monstrosity</type>
	    
	<alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
	    
	<ac>11</ac>
	    
	<hp>27 (6d6+6)</hp>
	    
	<speed>walk 20 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
	    
	<str>6</str>
	    
	<dex>12</dex>
	    
	<con>12</con>
	    
	<int>2</int>
	    
	<wis>13</wis>
	    
	<cha>5</cha>
	    
	<save/>
	    
	<skill/>
	    
	<passive>11</passive>
	    
	<languages/>
	    
	<cr>1/2</cr>
	    
	<resist/>
	    
	<immune/>
	    
	<vulnerable/>
	    
	<conditionImmune/>
	    
	<senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Bite</name>
		      
		<text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 3 (1d4 + 1) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 11 Constitution saving throw against being magically petrified. On a failed save, the creature begins to turn to stone and is restrained. It must repeat the saving throw at the end of its next turn. On a success, the effect ends. On a failure, the creature is petrified for 24 hours.</text>
		      
		<attack>Bite|+3|1d4+1</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<description>The cockatrice looks like a hideous hybrid of lizard, bird, and bat, and it is infamous for its ability to turn flesh to stone. These omnivores have a diet that consists of berries, nuts, flowers, and small animals such as insects, mice, and frogs-things they can swallow whole. They would be no threat to anything else if not for their fierce and frenzied response to even a hint of danger. A cockatrice flies into the face of any threat, squawking and madly beating its wings as its head darts out to peck. The smallest scratch from a cockatrice's beak can spell doom as its victim slowly turns to stone from the injury.Source: Monster Manual p. 42, Tales from the Yawning Portal, Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus, Eberron: Rising from the Last War, Mythic Odysseys of Theros</description>
	    
	<environment>grassland</environment>
	    
</monster>
