<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<monster>
	      
	<name>Nightmare</name>
	    
	<size>L</size>
	    
	<type>fiend</type>
	    
	<alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
	    
	<ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
	    
	<hp>68 (8d10+24)</hp>
	    
	<speed>walk 60 ft., fly 90 ft.</speed>
	    
	<str>18</str>
	    
	<dex>15</dex>
	    
	<con>16</con>
	    
	<int>10</int>
	    
	<wis>13</wis>
	    
	<cha>15</cha>
	    
	<save/>
	    
	<skill/>
	    
	<passive>11</passive>
	    
	<languages>understands Abyssal, Common, and Infernal but can't speak </languages>
	    
	<cr>3</cr>
	    
	<resist/>
	    
	<immune>fire</immune>
	    
	<vulnerable/>
	    
	<conditionImmune/>
	    
	<senses/>
	    
	<trait>
		        
		<name>Confer Fire Resistance</name>
		      
		<text>The nightmare can grant resistance to fire damage to anyone riding it.</text>
		      
	</trait>
	    
	<trait>
		        
		<name>Illumination</name>
		      
		<text>The nightmare sheds bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet.</text>
		      
	</trait>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Hooves</name>
		      
		<text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 7 (2d6) fire damage.</text>
		      
		<attack>Hooves|+6|2d8+4</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Ethereal Stride</name>
		      
		<text>The nightmare and up to three willing creatures within 5 feet of it magically enter the Ethereal Plane from the Material Plane, or vice versa.</text>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<description>A nightmare appears in a cloud of roiling smoke, its mane, tail, and hooves wreathed in flame. The creature's unearthly black form moves with supernatural speed, vanishing in a cloud of brimstone as quickly as it appeared.Dread Steed. Also called a &quot;demon horse&quot; or &quot;hell horse,&quot; the nightmare serves as a steed for creatures of exceptional evil, carrying demons, devils, death knights, liches, night hags, and other vile monsters. It resembles a fiendish horse, and a nightmare's fiery red eyes betray its malevolent intelligence. A nightmare can be summoned from the Lower Planes, but unless a worthy sacrifice is offered to it as food upon its arrival, the nightmare displays no special loyalty to the creature it serves.Creating a Nightmare. Nightmares don't appear naturally in the multiverse. They must be created from pegasi. The ritual that creates a nightmare requires the torturous removal of a pegasus's wings, driving that noble creature to evil as it is transformed by dark magic.Source: Monster Manual p. 235, Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus, Infernal Machine Rebuild, Mythic Odysseys of Theros</description>
	    
	<environment/>
	    
</monster>
