<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<monster>
	      
	<name>Noble</name>
	    
	<size>M</size>
	    
	<type>humanoid (any race)</type>
	    
	<alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
	    
	<ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
	    
	<hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
	    
	<speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
	    
	<str>11</str>
	    
	<dex>12</dex>
	    
	<con>11</con>
	    
	<int>12</int>
	    
	<wis>14</wis>
	    
	<cha>16</cha>
	    
	<save/>
	    
	<skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
	    
	<passive>12</passive>
	    
	<languages>any two languages</languages>
	    
	<cr>1/8</cr>
	    
	<resist/>
	    
	<immune/>
	    
	<vulnerable/>
	    
	<conditionImmune/>
	    
	<senses/>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Rapier</name>
		      
		<text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
		      
		<attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<reaction>
		        
		<name>Parry</name>
		      
		<text>The noble adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, the noble must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
		      
	</reaction>
	    
	<description>Nobles wield great authority and influence as members of the upper class, possessing wealth and connections that can make them as powerful as monarchs and generals. A noble often travels in the company of guards, as well as servants who are commoners.The noble's statistics can also be used to represent courtiers who aren't of noble birth.Source: Monster Manual p. 348, Curse of Strahd, Hoard of the Dragon Queen, Princes of the Apocalypse, Rise of Tiamat, Storm King's Thunder, Tales from the Yawning Portal, Tomb of Annihilation, Waterdeep: Dragon Heist, Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage, Ghosts of Saltmarsh, Essentials Kit: Divine Contention, Essentials Kit: Dragon of Icespire Peak, Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus, Eberron: Rising from the Last War, Infernal Machine Rebuild, Explorer's Guide to Wildemount, Mythic Odysseys of Theros, Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden</description>
	    
	<environment/>
	    
</monster>
