<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<monster>
	      
	<name>Spy</name>
	    
	<size>M</size>
	    
	<type>humanoid (any race)</type>
	    
	<alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
	    
	<ac>12</ac>
	    
	<hp>27 (6d8)</hp>
	    
	<speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
	    
	<str>10</str>
	    
	<dex>15</dex>
	    
	<con>10</con>
	    
	<int>12</int>
	    
	<wis>14</wis>
	    
	<cha>16</cha>
	    
	<save/>
	    
	<skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Investigation +5, Perception +6, Persuasion +5, Sleight of hand +4, Stealth +4</skill>
	    
	<passive>16</passive>
	    
	<languages>any two languages</languages>
	    
	<cr>1</cr>
	    
	<resist/>
	    
	<immune/>
	    
	<vulnerable/>
	    
	<conditionImmune/>
	    
	<senses/>
	    
	<trait>
		        
		<name>Cunning Action</name>
		      
		<text>On each of its turns, the spy can use a bonus action to take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action.</text>
		      
	</trait>
	    
	<trait>
		        
		<name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
		      
		<text>The spy deals an extra 7 (2d6) damage when it hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of the spy that isn't incapacitated and the spy doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
		      
	</trait>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Multiattack</name>
		      
		<text>The spy makes two melee attacks.</text>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Shortsword</name>
		      
		<text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
		      
		<attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<action>
		        
		<name>Hand Crossbow</name>
		      
		<text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
		      
		<attack>Hand Crossbow|+4|1d6+2</attack>
		      
	</action>
	    
	<description>Rulers, nobles, merchants, guildmasters, and other wealthy individuals use spies to gain the upper hand in a world of cutthroat politics. A spy is trained to secretly gather information. Loyal spies would rather die than divulge information that could compromise them or their employers.Source: Monster Manual p. 349, Curse of Strahd, Hoard of the Dragon Queen, Princes of the Apocalypse, Storm King's Thunder, Tomb of Annihilation, Waterdeep: Dragon Heist, Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage, Ghosts of Saltmarsh, Essentials Kit: Dragon of Icespire Peak, Essentials Kit: Storm Lord's Wrath, Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus, Eberron: Rising from the Last War, Infernal Machine Rebuild, Explorer's Guide to Wildemount, Mythic Odysseys of Theros, Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden</description>
	    
	<environment/>
	    
</monster>
